Theodorus Bailey Papers
Theodorus Bailey Papers
1828-1877
Bailey, Theodorus, 1805-1877.
0.5 linear ft.
Papers of the Admiral, United States Navy. Collection includes correspondence (1828-1874), much of which relates to Bailey's Civil War service; naval orders, circulars, reports and directives, and personal memorabilia.
148825
Biographical History
Admiral Theodorus Bailey was born in Chauteaugay, New York on April 12, 1805. He received his academic education in Plattsburg, New York and, at the age of thirteen, received a warrant as a midshipman in the Navy. His first cruise was in the corvette Cyane which provided a convoy for the first black colonists to Liberia, settling them on the Island of Sherboo, off the coast of Africa. During this cruise Bailey participated in the capture of a brig and six schooners which were illegally engaged in the slave trade.
Following several years of apprenticeship at sea, Bailey received the store-ship Lexington as his first command in 1846. It was during this period that he participated in the blockade and eventual seizure of lower California during the Mexican War. His next command, on the sloop-of-war St. Mary, detailed him to the Pacific Squadron and led him on an around-the-world cruise. During this time he was involved in the removal of the United States Consul in the Canary Islands, and was instrumental in quelling the Panama Riots of 1856.
When the Civil War began in 1861, Admiral Bailey tendered his services to the Union and was assigned to active duty as commander of the frigate Colorado in the blockade of Florida. In 1862, he was made second-in-command under David Farragut in the attack on New Orleans, Louisiana. Admiral Bailey led the Union fleet up the Mississippi River and accepted the surrender of New Orleans.
From 1862 to 1864, Admiral Bailey was commander of the East Gulf Blockading Squadron in the Gulf of Mexico, and subsequently had charge of the Portsmouth, New Hampshire, Navy Yard. He was promoted to Rear Admiral in 1866, and retired from active duty to accept a position on the Navy Retiring Board. He died February 10, 1877 in Washington, D.C.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Theodorus Bailey Papers consists of correspondence, memorabilia, legal and financial records, and official records.
Correspondence, the bulk of the collection, deals with the Admiral's career as a naval officer. Noteworthy correspondence includes letters from Napoleon Collins and Henry Pinkney, both dated July 30, 1842, concerning a duel between H.H. Rhodes and Admiral Bailey. Also of interest is a letter that describes the attack on New Orleans written by Admiral Bailey to an unknown acquaintance on May 5, 1862, and a letter, dated November 7, 1865, from William G. McEwan to William Oland Bourn, editor of Soldiers Friend, enclosing a manuscript describing McEwan's participation in the August 5, 1864 Battle of Mobile Bay, Alabama. In addition, two letters addressed to Admiral Bailey from John W. Hogg and George D. Allen, dated July 8 and July 18, 1873 respectively, deal with the distribution of prize monies due from the capture of rebel privateers during the War. Letters from Admiral Bailey to his son, Edmund S., during the war years, also cover this topic thoroughly. A complete index to the correspondence can be found at the end of this inventory.
Memorabilia includes biographical material, engraving, obituaries, and miscellaneous material. An undated holograph biographical sketch, including an account of the Admiral's ancestors, comprises the biographical material. The engravings portray the Admiral when he was promoted to commander in 1849. The miscellaneous material, undated, is a poem, "Lord Lovell," and a copy of it made by Sallie Bailey.
Legal and financial records consists of deeds to property owned by Admiral Bailey and receipts for life insurance and letters received.
Official records includes circulars, general orders, petitions, proclamations, reports, and miscellaneous material. Circulars, 1854-1862, are military suggestions or statements and are in chronological order, as are the general orders, 1862-1864, which involve prescribed methods or directives for military action. The material included as petitions, 1868, and reports, 1869, deals with the attack on New Orleans which occurred April 24, 1862, and a resultant misrepresentation of the facts concerning Admiral Bailey's participation. Miscellaneous items, 1857-1872, consist of legal papers, requisitions, weights of the USS Colorado at mean draft 23'3, lists of prizes captured by the East Coast Blockade Squadron, and British and American Claims (Wm. Bowman vs. U.S.).
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically with envelopes included at the end of the section. A complete index to the correspondence can be found at the end of this inventory. Memorabilia is arranged alphabetically by subject matter. Legal and financial records are organized chronologically. Official records are arranged alphabetically by type.
Subject and Genre Headings
Military history; Politics, government and public administration; Bailey, Theodorus, 1805-1877.; Farragut, David Glasgow, 1801-1870.; McKean, William W. (William Wister), 1800-1865.; Porter, David D. (David Dixon), 1813-1891.; Temple, William Grenville.; Welles, Gideon, 1802-1878.; United States. -- Navy. -- Officers.; Admirals -- United States.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Naval operations.; Correspondence.; Memorabilia.; Admirals.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 1969.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - [General], 1828; 1840,; 1842 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1846 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1852; 1857,; 1858 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1861 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1862; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - [General], 1863 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1864 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1865-1867; 1869 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1871; 1873,; 1874 (Box 1)
  - Envelopes (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Biographical material, undated (Box 1)
  - Engravings, Com. Theodorus Bailey, 1849 (Box 1)
  - Obituaries, 1877 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, poem "Lord Lovell," copy by Sallie Bailey, undated (Box 1)
- Legal and financial records
  - Deeds, 1852 (Box 1)
  - Receipts, 1855; 1861,; 1863-1864 (Box 1)
- Official records
  - Circulars, 1854-1855; 1861,; 1862; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - General Orders, 1862; 1863,; 1864; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Petition, by Bailey for Naval Board of Inquiry into Attack on New Orleans by fleet under Admiral Farragut, 1868; holo., holo. copy (Box 1)
  - Prociamations, May 1, 1862; pr. mat. (Box 1)
  - Report, "Attack on New Orleans," History Set Right, 1869; pub. mat. (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Legal papers, 1857; 1862 (Box 1)
    - Supply requisition, 1862 (Box 1)
    - Weights of the "Colorado" at mean draft 23'3", 1862 (Box 1)
    - Lists of prizes captured by East Coast Blockade Squadron, 1862-1863 (Box 1)
    - British and American Claims, Wm Bowman vs. U.S., 1864-1872; pr. mat. (Box 1)
Index to correspondence
Letters are indexed by sender only. For ease of reading, names with many dates have been divided by year. So for example, there are two entries for William Wister McKean: "McKean, Wm. Wister, 1861" and "McKean, Wm. Wister, 1862."
Alden, James and Porter, David D. 1862 Mar 14 USS "Richmond" off Ship Isl'd. Miss. Sound to Theodorus Bailey
Allen, George D. 1873 Jul 18 Key West, Florida to Theodorus Bailey
Bailey, Theodorus, 1846 and earlier 1828 Apr 25 Navy Yard, N.Y.C. to Samuel L. Southar 1846 Jun 4 USS "Lexington"
Bailey, Theodorus, 1861 Jun 5 USS "Colorado" to Edmund S. Bailey Jul 15 USS "Colorado" to Charley ? Aug 1 USS "Colorado" off Fort Pickens, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Aug 20 USS "Colorado" off Pensacola, Fla. to William Mervine Aug 26 USS "Colorado" off South West Pass, Miss. Delta to John H. Russell Nov 27 USS "Colorado" off South West Pass, Miss. Delta to Edmund S. Bailey Dec 26 USS "Colorado" off South West Pass, Miss. Delta to Edmund S. Bailey
Bailey, Theodorus, 1862 Jan 30 USS "Colorado" off South West Pass, Miss. Delta to Edmund S. Bailey Feb 20 USS "Colorado" off South West Pass, Miss. Delta to John L. Davis Mar 6 USS "Colorado" off Pensacola, Fla to Edmund S. Bailey Mar 14 USS "Colorado" off Ship Isl'd., Miss. Sound to Edmund S. Bailey Apr 12 South West Pass, Miss. Delta to Edmund S. Bailey Apr 20 USS "Oneida" Miss. River to David G. Farragut Apr 25 USS "Cayuga" off New Orleans, Miss. to David G. Farragut Apr 25 USS "Cayuga" Hampton Roads, Va. to Gideon Welles May 5 USS "Cayuga" off Key West, Fla. to ? Aug 5 Sacketts Harbor Station, N.Y. to Edmund S. Bailey Sep 19 Sacketts Harbor Station, N.Y. to Edmund S. Bailey Oct 12 Sacketts Harbor Station, N.Y. to T. Bailey Myers Oct 25 Sacketts Harbor Station, N.Y. to T. Bailey Myers Nov 13 N.Y.C. Gideon Welles
Bailey, Theodorus, 1863 Jan 3 Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Jan 18 USS "San Jacinto" Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Jan 19 USS "St. Lawrence" Key West, Fla. to ? Jan 25 USS "St. Lawrence" Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Feb 9 USS "St. Lawrence" Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Feb 28 USS "St. Lawrence" Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Mar 29 USS "St. Lawrence" Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Apr 20 USS "St. Lawrence" Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Apr 29 USS "St. Lawrence" Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey May 31 USS "St. Lawrence" Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Jun 12 USS "Magnolia" Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Jul 1 USS "Magnolia" Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Jul 11 USS "San Jacinto" Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Jul 24 USS "San Jacinto" Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Aug 12 USS "San Jacinto" Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Aug 17 USS "San Jacinto" Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Aug 22 USS USS "San Jacinto" Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Aug 27 USS "San Jacinto" Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Sep 14 USS "San Jacinto" Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Sep 27 USS "San Jacinto" Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Oct 9 USS "San Jacinto" Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Oct 16 USS "Dale" to Edmund S. Bailey Oct 27 USS "San Jacinto" Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Nov 10 USS "San Jacinto" Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Nov 24 USS "San Jacinto" Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Dec 3 USS "San Jacinto" Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Dec 6 USS "San Jacinto" Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey
Bailey, Theodorus, 1864 Feb 11 Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Mar 17 Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Apr 2 Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey May 11 Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey May 28 Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Jun 6 USS "Dale" Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Jun 9 "USS "Dale" Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Jun 24 USS "Dale" Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Jul 11 Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Jul 14 Key West, Fla. to Edmund S. Bailey Sep 20 Oyster Bay, Long Isl'd., N. Y. to Gideon Welles
Bailey, Theodorus, 1865 and later 1865 Nov 30 Navy Dept., Washington, D. C. to Charles Walters 1866 Dec 29 US Navy Yard, Portsmouth, N. H. to George H. Preble 1874 Feb 10 Washington, D. C. to Mary B. McKnight
Bell, Henry Haywood 1863 Dec 18 USS "Pensacola" off New Orleans, Mississippi to Theodorus Bailey
Carter, George B. 1861 Sep 13 USS "Colorado" to William Mervine
Collins, Napoleon 1842 Jul 30 Hong Kong to John J. Reynolds
Davis, John L. 1862 Apr 9 USS "Colorado" off South West Pass, Miss. Delta to Theodorus Bailey
Dupont, Samuel F. 1852 Jun 24 near Wilmington, Delaware to Theodorus Bailey
Farragut, David G., 1862 Feb 22 USS "Hartford" off Ship Isl'd., Miss. Sound to Theodorus Bailey Feb 24 USS "Hartford" off Ship Isl'd., Miss. Sound to Theodorus Bailey Feb 29 USS "Hartford" off Ship Isl'd., Miss. Sound to Theodorus Bailey Mar 7 USS "Hartford" at mouth of Miss. River to Theodorus Bailey Mar 8 USS "Hartford" at Pass A L'outre, Miss. Delta, to Theodorus Bailey1862 Mar 8 USS "Hartford" at Pass A L'outre, Miss. Delta to Theodorus Bailey Mar 12 USS "Hartford" at South West Pass, Miss. Delta to Theodorus Bailey Mar 12 USS "Hartford" at South West Pass, Miss. Delta to Theodorus Bailey Mar 13 USS "Hartford" at South West Pass, Miss. Delta to Theodorus Bailey Mar 19 USS "Colorado" Ship Isl'd., Miss. Sound to Theodorus Bailey Apr 3 USS "Richmond" to Theodorus Bailey Apr 7 Pilot Town to Theodorus Bailey Apr 9 USS "Hartford" to Theodorus Bailey Apr 9 USS "Hartford" to Theodorus Bailey Apr 11 USS "Hartford" to Theodorus Bailey Apr 27 USS "Hartford" off New Orleans, La. to Theodorus Bailey Jun 11 USS "Hartford" off Baton Rouge, La. to Theodorus Bailey Aug 28 USS "Hartford" at Pensacola Bay, Florida to ?
Farragut, David G., 1864 Feb 19 USS "Hartford" at Ship Isl'd., Miss. Sound to Theodorus Bailey Apr 4 Richmond (?) to Theodorus Bailey to Theodorus Bailey May 26 USS "Hartford" off Mobile, Ala. to Theodorus Bailey Jun 14 USS "Hartford" off Mobile, Ala. to Theodorus Bailey Jul 16 USS "Tennessee" off Mobile, Ala. to Theodorus Bailey
Halter, R. E. 1862 Mar 11 South West Pass, Miss. Delta to Theodorus Bailey
Harrison, N. B. 1869 Apr 19 Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md. to Theodorus Bailey
Hogg, John W. 1873 Jul 8 Navy Dept., Washington, D. C. to Theodorus Bailey
Horner, G. R. B. 1861 Feb 20 USS "Colorado" to Theodorus Bailey 1861 Aug 14 USS "Colorado" off Fort Pickens, Fla. to Theodorus Bailey 1862 Feb 22 USS "Colorado" off South West Pass Miss. Delta to Theodorus Bailey
Lee, Samuel Phillips 1862 Mar 7 USS "Oneida" at mouth of Miss. River to Theodorus Bailey
McEwan, William G. 1865 Nov 7 Navy Yard, Philadelphia, Pa to Wm. Oland Bourn
McKean, Wm. Wister, 1861 Jan 3 USS "Niagara" off Ship Isl'd., Miss. Sound to Theodorus Bailey Sep 28 USS "Niagara" off Pass A L'outre, to Theodorus Bailey Oct 7 USS "Niagara" off Pass A L'outre, to Theodorus Bailey Oct 7 USS "Niagara" off Ship Isl'd., Miss. Sound to Theodorus Bailey Oct 15 USS "Niagara" off Fort Pickens, Fla. to Theodorus Bailey Oct 31 USS "Niagara" off South West Pass Miss. Delta to Theodorus Bailey Nov 8 USS "Niagara" off South West Pass Miss. Delta to Theodorus Bailey Nov 13 USS "Niagara" off South West Pass Miss. Delta to Theodorus Bailey Nov 15 USS "Niagara" off Ship Isl'd., Miss. Delta to Theodorus Bailey Dec 19 USS "Niagara" to Theodorus Bailey Dec 19 USS "Niagara" off Fort Pickens, Fla. to Theodorus Bailey Dec 26 USS "Niagara" off Ship Island Miss. Sound to Theodorus Bailey
McKean, Wm. Wister, 1862 Jan 3 USS "Niagara" off Ship Island Miss. Sound to Theodorus Bailey Jan 3 USS "Niagara" off Ship Island Miss. Sound to Theodorus Bailey Jan 20 USS "Niagara" off Ship Island Miss. Sound to Theodorus Bailey Jan 21 USS "Niagara" off Ship Island Miss. Sound to Theodorus Bailey Feb 3 USS "Niagara" off South West Pass Miss. Delta to Theodorus Bailey Feb 13 USS "Niagara" to Theodorus Bailey
Mervine, William 1861 Sep. 21 USS "Colorado" off Fort Pickens, Fla. New York to Theodorus Bailey
Morton, Thomas H. 1871 Jun 2 New York to Theodorus Bailey
Paulding, James Kirke 1840 Jun 15 Navy Dept, Washington, D. C. to Theodorus Bailey
Pinkney, Henry 1842 Jul 30 Hong Kong to Theodorus Bailey
Porter, David D. 1863 Jul 3 USS "Black Hawk" Miss. Squadron to J. C. Febiger 1863 Aug 6 USS "Black Hawk" Miss. Squadron to J. C. Febiger 1864 Oct 22 Hampton Roads, Va. to Theodorus Bailey 1864 Nov 4 USS "Malbern" Hampton Roads, Va. to R. W. Meade 1867 Jul 17 Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md. to Charles Sumner
Putnam, James O. 1861 Dec 13 U. S. Consulate, Le Havre, France to William H. Seward
Reynolds, William 1858 Nov 12 Honolulu, Hawaii to Theodorus Bailey 1863 Mar 7 USS "Vermont" Port Royal, S. C. to Theodorus Bailey
Robeson, George M. 1869 Oct 12 Navy Dept., Washington, D. C. to Theodorus Bailey
Rogers, John A. 1861 Jan 23 South West Pass, Miss. Delta to Theodorus Bailey 1862 Jan 12 USS "Samuel Rotan" to Theodorus Bailey
Ross, W. N. N. T. 1861 Dec 13 USS "Desperato" off Mississippi River to William Mervine
Schenck, James F. 1864 Oct 15 USS "Powhatan", Hampton Roads, Va. to Theodorus Bailey
Selfridge, Thomas O. 1861 Dec 10 USS "Mississippi" off Pass A L'outre, Miss. Delta to Theodorus Bailey
Shufeldt, Robert W. 1861 Dec 18 to U. S. Consulate General, Havana, Cuba Commander at Key West
Smith, Melancton 1861 Sep. 20 USS "Massachusetts" off Ship Island, Miss. Sound to William Mervine
Temple, Wm. Grenville 1864 May 27 Washington, D. C. to Theodorus Bailey 1864 Jun 1 Washington, D. C. to Theodorus Bailey 1864 Jun 8 Washington, D. C. to Theodorus Bailey 1864 Jun 28 Washington, D. C. to Theodorus Bailey 1864 Jul 17 Bordentown, N. J. to Theodorus Bailey 1864 Aug 7 Bordentown, N. J. to Bowman (?) 1864 Aug 20 Rutland, Vermont to Theodorus Bailey 1864 Oct 16 Cold Spring, Putnam County, N.Y. to Theodorus Bailey 1864 Nov 22 USS "Pontoosuc" Navy Yard, N.Y. to Theodorus Bailey 1865 Feb 12 USS "Pontoosuc" Cape Fear River, North Carolina to Theodorus Bailey 1865 Feb 21 USS "Pontoosuc" Four miles below Wilmington, Va. to Theodorus Bailey 1865 Mar 25 USS "Pontoosuc" James River to Theodorus Bailey 1865 Apr 9 USS "Pontoosuc" Hampton Roads, Va. to Theodorus Bailey 1865 Jul 12 Rutland, Vermont to Theodorus Bailey 1866 Jul 31 USS "Tacony" Charleston, S. C. to Theodorus Bailey 1866 Oct 21 USS "Tacony" Hampton Roads, Va. to Theodorus Bailey
Toucey, Isaac 1857 Mar 21 Navy Department, Washington, D. C. to Theodorus Bailey
Walker, W. M. 1862 Feb 11 USS "DeSoto" to Theodorus Bailey Feb 11 USS "DeSoto" to Theodorus Bailey
Welles, Gideon 1861 Apr 27 Navy Department, Washington, D.C. to William L.Hudson 1861 Dec 30 Navy Department, Washington, D. C. to Wm. Wister McKean